CHAPTER 4

Disability in Cinema
A Case Study of Selected Hindi Films

KURUKHETRA DIP

INTRODUCTION

Cinema is considered one of the most acceptable forms of art in the contemporary era. In cinema or through cinema, we can see what is happening in society and aspire for society through cinematic imagination. The study of films provides opportunities to connect history and technology vis-à-vis social changes and ideological impetus. Over time, cinema production has also gone through several changes due to changes in technological advancement. The relevance of watching traditional theatre is also changing due to the availability of DVDs/CDs and other online streaming mediums for watching movies. In other words, films or cinema is more accessible to general contours than ever before. With time, the study of films and film studies has also changed. Now many traditional disciplines like philosophy, political science, sociology, etc., are studying film/cinema from their disciplinary point of view.

Different disciplinary perspective gives a slightly different reading of a film. For example, ‘Anthropology of Film’ might integrate ethnography into films and read it as ‘seeing culture’ of a particular period or point in time. At the same time, from the ‘sociological lens’, the reading of the same movie might look upon the sociological aspects, i.e., gender, race, community, etc., interpreted in that. For instance, in the film Dilwale Dulhania Le Jayenge an anthropological argument would be how the Indian diaspora can inculcate their cultural values, whereas from the sociological point of view, how ‘patriarchy and power’ work in modern/advanced society. In the history department, films can be viewed in their historical context. In the mass media and cultural studies departments, perhaps the cousins of sociology in terms of film analysis, the reader is asked to consider social and cultural powers in making a film and the film industry. Further, sociologists can engage in decoding a film and explain how films elicit structure and facilitate the expression of different emotions to which human are subjects to. Reading films with a sociological eye makes us conscious of ourselves as we watch movies. As we are being entertained, we are also introduced to the worldviews and social theories embedded in the films.

Sociological reading of films asks us to look beyond common sense thinking and long-held interpretations. If we take film/cinema as text or literature, it speaks a lot about social issues and turbulences that society experiences. In this context, cinema as literature is appreciable not because of its capacity to tell us a good story but rather how ‘the scriptwriter’ reflects and approaches the social context, social/psychological struggles, etc. One can understand a social class to which we generally do not belong and do not associate our feelings with it, through the vantage point provided in cinematic narratives. Like, a novel’s interpretation lies on the readers; a movie’s readings also depend on its audience. It depends on how the audience decodes it and how it imagines itself with the ‘galaxy of images’ presented in a movie. Further, it also depends on how the audience thinks of movies as comprising visual languages, verbal systems, dialogue, characterization, narrative, and story (Slied: 2001, 3).

In artistic and expressive mediums, i.e., cinema and television1 they use narratives with little tweaks that are already popular in larger imagination. The appearance of disabilities in these imaginations is quite different from physical disability and cognitive disorders. Physical disability appears to be a challenge and tragedy whereas, in the case of cognitive disorder, it appeals in a somewhat different role. Audiences are typically asked to respond in a restricted number of ways, ranging from sympathy or pity to some sort of charitable granting of limited personality to such characters. They avoid complicated characters and adopt a simple loving protagonist that can be understandable, so the show will succeed in masses. Furthermore, these narratives ease the audiences about their idea of ‘normalcy’. In many cases, if the movie’s lead character is a ‘cognitive disorder’ or ‘madness’, i.e., depression, schizophrenia, etc., the protagonist becomes a tragic stand-in for its audiences. In this regard, Davis (32) argued that the line between tragedy and redemption, as well as between tragedy and comedy, seems to be blurred by obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD). In one scenario, the person with OCD is transformed into a cute little nut and called a disability ‘mascot’ (ibid.), and this mascotization of disability produces a loveable and cuddly represent-ation of disability.

Similarly, if a side character has a disability and the movie is not about disability, then the viewers may be inattentive because of the disability narrative. In an ableist culture, they would question why the ‘normalcy’ of the movie is being altered. In this view, a disability is an allegory because it must represent something else, i.e., weakness, insecurity, bitterness, fragility, evil, innocence, etc., and be the setting for the moral lesson that people are good and can overcome obstacles, and that we shouldn’t be prejudiced or dejected.

THEORETICAL CONUNDRUM

One can say that the semiotic code of cinema is the semiotic code of reality. The echoes of a similar argument can be found in canonical film theory as well as in the ‘cognitive code’ of reality given by Pasolini (1968). Representation in cinema is about allegorical interpretation rather than just being confined to the interpretative meaning of images. Cinema can be seen as a vehicle of abstraction, given that the symbolic meaning of the filmic image derives from the symbolic value of cinema. However, such inference is always in strain with the film’s signifier and signified, which ensures that such a moment is not abstract but embodied. It is in this context,

One might suggest that the question posed by van Dormael’s film is precisely how far the socially mediated concept of disability is perceived through the ontological assertion of bodies captured in cinematic representation intertwines with other concepts such as community nation and humanness (Fraser: 2016).

One has to acknowledge that, the thinking process influences our apprehension and our vision has an impact on knowledge. Through films, audiences may get an idea of how disability is deep-seated in a given social setting along with their encounter about how disability is socially mediated in other cultures. Whether perceived as negative, positive, or neutral, the individual and social forces that create and shape the appearance of a disability in cinema motivate those forces to act in the way they do. As Fraser (2016) also argued, the appearance of disability in movies and its portrayal in media always seem important but it never appealed to the global context.

No matter what the textures of cinematic representation discussed, and no matter where they unfold across the globe, it is in analysing, evaluating, and comprehending the ideas behind the creation and viewing of movies, it is via the interrogation of social formations of visual knowledge that viewers may move towards other ways of seeing. In this way, the worldwide cinema serves as the beginning of a discussion about representation, a process that naturally also takes place outside of the context of artistic debate in our day-to-day interactions with one another (Fraser: 2016) as Siebers’ once said ‘representation is the difference that makes a difference’ (2008, 17).

Social representations necessarily mediate the cognitive codes we use to construct realities, and as such, they are also potentially impacted, shaped, grounded and re-calibrated by artistic representations. ‘How do we accept peoples’ belief systems, the attitudes, ideas, and conceptualization of people with disabilities?’ The staging of disability for global audiences and readerships thus begins a meaningful conversation on attitudinal change. If ‘disability enlarges our vision of human variation and difference’ (Siebers: 2010, 3), then consideration of disability across world cinema contexts will have enlarged our world a great deal more indeed. In a global context, there are certain assertions in movies like Oasis (Lee Chang-dong, 2002) and disability discourse in New Wave Korean movies, that the fiction film spans ‘two gendered modalities, simultaneously spotlighting a male crisis while anticipating a more expansive take on female subjectivity’ (Fraser: 2016).

DISABILITY IN CINEMA

The understanding of Disability is quite tragic compared to other concepts used in social and political theory. In the time of enlightenment, and later philosophers/social theorists were quite in a corner to study disability from the preview of their theory or philosophy for that matter. Studying disability in concrete contexts of able-nationalism, Snyder and Mitchell’s issue offered an opportunity for scholars to pursue a new paradigm for theorizing disability among other cross-cultural experiences of bodies identified as deviant (2010a, 119). They further argued that the problem with disability studies is that they transport theories and methodology from the Western academy to the other parts and give local disability structures and understandings barely passing consideration (2010, 219). Disability, as Siebers (2010, 4-5) wrote,

was present even if ‘rarely recognized as such throughout the history of modern art, where the presence of disability of “strangeness” and the “convulsive”; of “misshapen and twisted bodies” allowed the beauty of artwork to endure over time’.

As a visual medium, cinema-like painting, and sculpture, for example, have not focused on the representation of bodies: bodies in specific locations, accurate and imagined.

DISABILITY NARRATIVES IN HINDI CINEMA

The majority of people in India misunderstand disability because of a lack of awareness and as a consequence, people with disability live in constant marginalization. Looking into this lack of awareness one can take the help of a representational medium that can provide a powerful platform for the dissemination of knowledge and reach out to the masses in a short period. In this context looking to the outreach of Bollywood or Hindi film industry, one can use it as an effective tool to connect people and sensitize about disability and its related stereotypes. Indian cinema in general and Hindi cinema in particular, in their earlier narratives, adopted a normative approach to ‘fixing’ disability, in which a disabled person is introduced to an able-bodied person who teaches them how to put aside their impairment and leads happy lives. The following paragraphs offer some examples of such.

In early narratives, disability can be seen as a punishment (Jeevan Naiya, 1936; Kashish, 1980; Dhaiwan, 1981). But in Netrikakan (1981) the message was both punishment as well as desexualization of persons with disabilities. Another narrative is that being disabled is a worse punishment than death (Sholay, 1975). Apart from these narrations, disability can also seen as stigma, mockery and restoration of normalcy (Guzaarish, 2010; Koi… Mil Gaya, 2003; Pyare Mohan, 2006; Tom, Dick, and Harry, 2006).

Until the 2000s, the representation of disability in Hindi films was very offensive, and caricatural in nature. Things have changed with the new wave of cinema, the representative narration changed, now it has become sensible and directly engaged with the subject. Even in the new wave cinema, certain films continue the old fashion. The primary objective is to use the platform to increase public sensitivity and awareness of the issue. Additionally, it appears that the way a director views disability has shifted from being something to exploit to being seen from the perspective of the disabled person. This change in the line of thinking can be dated back to 2005 when the nation’s first international film festival for people with disabilities was held by the Chennai-based NGO Ability Foundation. The festival’s goal was to dispel misconceptions about people with disabilities and raise awareness of disability issues through an extraordinary showcase of international films (Indiaglitz). Since then, this festival has been held annually and has attracted several notable producers and directors.

Along with increased sensitivity, mainstream movies about a variety of ailments have recently come out, including Progeria, Alzheimer’s, Dyslexia, Asperger syndrome and Cerebral Palsy. It is encouraging to see that many of these movies are edging closer to presenting disability as an integral part of society. Although some of these films have been criticized for stereotyping, it is still important to appreciate them because the ideas they explore have never even been depicted on film.

AS LANGUAGE

Like silences, discourses are not subservient to or opposed to authority. Discourse communicates and creates power, it maintains it, but sometimes it undermines and exposes it, weakens it, and allows it to be thwarted. Similarly, silence and secrecy provide a haven for authority, cementing its prohibitions, but they also relax its grip and allow for relatively hidden pockets of tolerance. Dialogue is linguistic usage, in whatever form and via whatever means, concerning social, political, and cultural formations; it reflects social order, but it is also language producing social order and defining social life negotiation. Studies from racism2 language in usage can impact people’s lives in both ‘good’ and ‘bad’ ways.

Regularized and ritualized ‘negative’ change has the same power to harm, oppress, and exclude racial and ethnic groups on both personal and institutionalized levels as the practical hurdles to inclusion that people with disabilities encounter in their daily lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in the lives of those who are denied access to the use of language or whose access is limited to the ‘basic’, ‘ordinary’, and ‘daily’ due to discriminatory educational and societal practices.

However, this narrow focus for linguistic oppression analysis may be a red herring in the context of resistance politics given that the production of meaning, cultural value, and patterns of access to discourse are inextricably linked with social relations of domination and subordination. Nevertheless, many sociolinguists concur that persuasive language is necessary to bring about significant social change in the face of oppressive structures of any kind. It needs to interact with the dominant discourses defining the key spheres of its social reproduction to compete in mainstream society. In last, Marx may have missed the fact that ‘to interpret it persuasively is to change it’ when he launched his famous war cry against conventional philosophy (the goal is not ‘to interpret the world differently but to change it’, as repeated by Oliver and Barnes).

DISABILITY AND SOCIAL ATTITUDE

When the elevator of her college stops working one day, Laila is hoisted up the steps in her wheelchair. This act calls into question the ableist culture's perception of staircases as ‘beautiful architectural elements [...] that raise key state buildings’. They are shown in the film as tyrannical and bigoted toward Laila, who has a physical impairment. Stairs signify a ‘commonplace cultural assumption’ in our society, ‘an embedded aspect of the interpretive frameworks sanctioned by culture’ that supports a specific view of the human body and its powers. This understanding of ableism as a practice working at the level of everyday discourse also offers options for us looking for alternatives that contradict ableist normativity, such as the presence of an elevator as an alternative.

Furthermore, scenes featuring Khanum and Laila playing miniature golf and swimming in New York and cricket in Delhi illustrate the film’s ableist discourse, which frequently dictates the underlying social structures of sport. There is no denying that certain sports favour and reward specific abilities or physical capacities. In this regard, Cherney’s (2011) views can help us understand the more nuanced of how societal attitudes help to create more hurdles for persons with disabilities. According to him,

The system of sports shapes expectations of physical capacity by designing games with rules that create spaces where individual performances and abilities appear salient, and it labels those whose bodies prevent them from participating as ‘disabled’ or ‘incapacitated’. (p. 6).

It might be claimed that comprehending the nature of such a system’s activities opens up opportunities for alternate methods of practicing existing sports and new ones. Furthermore, at Laila's college’s rock band competition, the woman handing out the top award to her college team states that it was granted to them because a girl with a handicap wrote the songs. In the film, the woman presenting the award tells Laila,

This competition is a milestone. When I was informed that a disabled musician had written the song’s lyrics, we had to give the award to her college. Your journey must have been different from other normal children. Would you like to share anything with us? (Bose: 2014).

To accommodate the different aspects of ‘persons with disability’, the role of other people’s attitudes towards them contributes a lot. Some of the films take such a stance where some of the other characters play that role to accommodate the difference. One such film is Taare Zameen Par where the story revolves around an eight-year-old Ishaan. He slowly lost his interest in study but was unaware of his dyslexia. Later, when his parents enrolled him in a boarding school, he could not cope with the new challenges thrown at him. However, his life changed when he met a temporary teacher Ram Nikumbh (Amir), a temporary relief teacher for ‘special needs students’. Ishaan can rediscover his self-confidence and overcome an impairment that his parents were unaware of with Nikumbh’s aid and advice. Aamir Khan’s directorial debut film shows Ishaan’s dyslexia sensitively and gives an emotional look at life as a youngster humiliated by an ignorant world. In his family, the dyslexia of Ishaan is unacceptable. When his father is not ready to accept that Ishaan has been suffering from dyslexia for a while, his mother accepts it and plays the sincere caregiver to her son. Later on, his father also accepts when Nikumbh confesses his suffering from dyslexia.

The film’s brilliance rests in Khan’s visual storytelling, which combines animation and live-action to provide viewers with insight into the mind of his young protagonist. His concentration on nuance prevents the picture from devolving into melodrama. He lets his gifted actors do the rest, particularly Safary, who gives an outstanding performance as the damaged but intelligent boy attempting to take his place in the world. Khan, a special-needs sibling, criticizes the Indian school system for producing geniuses while rejecting those it considers to be failures. In addition, the film critiques Indian society for failing these intelligent youngsters by ignoring their latent potential.

Another film, Main Aisa Hi Hoon (Baweja: 2005), shows multiple aspects of the problems faced by persons with disability. In this film, nobody is ready to understand or to say nobody is ready to accept Indraneel, an autistic single parent who is raising his seven-year-old daughter by all means. He works as a waiter in a coffee house, and his life revolves around his daughter and the coffee shop.

DISABILITY AND SEXUALITY

Quoting Merleau-Ponty (1963), Shildrick (2005) implies that sexuality is nothing more than a ‘mode of existence’. Shildrick also refers to Foucault, implying that bodies are equally made and susceptible to perpetual modification rather than fixed (Shildrick, 2005: 116). Based on all of these ideas, every type of disability provides its own unique set of sexual options within specific time-space settings that may or may not restrict other parts of identity performance. Because most sexuality is fundamentally about the interdependence and transmission of bodies, wills, and intentions, as well as an inherent vulnerability in which the boundaries of the Self and the Other are unpredictable, the subject is never settled or limited but intricately interwoven with the other in a dynamic process of becoming. Suppose one looks at the history of cinema carefully. In that case, it shows that many films have been made on the issues about women with disabilities from time to time as one of the most powerful and influential representational mediums for a while. The cinema both underrepresented and often misrepresented the issues regarding women with disabilities. Further, this notion is substantiated by how women with disabilities have been portrayed in the movie Barfi! (Basu: 2012) and Margarita with a Straw (Bose: 2015).

In these movies, the everyday language, attitudes, and actions depicted in films generate and reinforce sexist, ableist norms, resulting in various forms of discrimination and exploitation across specific locations and generations. In Barfi!, when Jhilmil realizes she has affection for Barfi, she attempts to mimic Shruti. She, like Shruti, strives to suck down a whole panipuri.3 Moreover, she tries to drape a sari but cannot do so independently. When the camera concentrates on scrutinizing her waist in the mirror to impress Barfi, her sexual impulses are accentuated. In Barfi!, a scenario in which the potential for sexual exploitation of disabled women in public places is highlighted by Barfi and Jhilmil as they are lying in a car while the man sitting next to them ogles Jhilmil’s bare calves in a voyeuristic manner. Although Barfi's mocking reaction of baring his legs and pointing the man to leer at them challenges the ableist patriarchal order of society’s ‘primordial desire for the pleasurable looking’ and sexual objectification of women, given his role as Jhilmil’s bodyguard, it fails to bring about any significant shifts in the ableist patriarchal order of society (Mulvey: 1975, 9).

Margarita with a Straw dares to deal with the disregarded and demonized component of sexual pleasure in Laila’s life. When she tries to tell her mother about her bisexuality, she displays a frequent hesitation to use the term ‘bisexual’ within ableist language. ‘Aai, I have become a “bi”.’4 She informs her mother after much deliberation and effort. Underlining an interesting wordplay, Laila’s mother misinterprets ‘bi’ as the Hindi term ‘bai’ for ‘servant’ and mockingly says, ‘Even I am a bai’. No matter how well-educated these Hindustani men are, they all refer to their spouses as bai (Bose: 2014). This demonstrates her mother’s ignorance and the danger to heterosexual ableist standards. Under the ableist umbrella of the film, it also carefully ties together LGBT and class problems. Furthermore, this scene is shot in a house courtyard, a woman’s place and an in-between area that, while open, is not a public space.

When Laila tries to confess her bisexuality for the second time, she does it in the confines of a bathtub while trying to bathe her ill mother. The bathroom, where the body is king and where secrecy, privacy, sexuality, and cleanliness are most openly practiced, is expertly employed as a venue that discloses one’s innermost impulses and secret kinds of pleasures. On the other hand, her mother fails to notice and instead repeats the earlier ‘bai’ joke, claiming that Laila has unquestionably become her ‘bai’ now that she has to care for and bathe her cancer-stricken mother. Furthermore, Laila’s slurred voice in the scene appears to show underlying inhibitions about using specific labels to describe sexuality. ‘Not the servant, bai?’ Her mother inquires. ‘What are you on about, bai?’ ‘What exactly does that imply?’ (Bose: 2014). Laila eventually tells her mother who Khanum is and her girlfriend. Her mother's initial response is revulsion, exclaiming, ‘Chiee, this is not natural!’ ‘This is what the world said about me as I grew up, and you fought with them,’ Laila says, reacting to contempt. This is hypocrisy since you are now behaving as if you were one of them’ (Bose: 2014).

As a result, if a person’s image is experienced and represented as a complex and ever-changing combination of physical, mental, and social mechanisms, a more nuanced understanding and tracing of both ableist constructs and mechanisms that question them is required. Both Jhilmil and Laila require an assistant or caretaker to assist them with dressing correctly, negotiating bathroom facilities, requiring physical provisioning and assistance in achieving comfortable sexual positions, and fulfilling other bodily demands. They participate more explicitly in such networks, which might be described as a type of tangential desire or desiring production for transformational possibilities of being and being in the Deleuzian sense (Deleuze & Guattari: 1987).

DISABILITY AND CHALLENGE TO
ABLEIST IDEOLOGY

Although they are scarce, it is vital to call attention to the tangential instances in the films covered here that poke and challenge the ableist discourse’s predominance. For instance, in Barfi!, when Jhilmil repeatedly sings her favourite song in a way that her class disapproves of during a birthday celebration, some of her snobbish society members make fun of her, Jhilmil responds by calling them out. Furthermore, the theme of glass surfaces, mirrors, automobile headlights, and a glass paperweight, which Jhilmil receives from her grandpa, gives imperfect views of objects and unsettles the film’s ableist discourse by altering the audience’s order world view. Jhilmil is frequently shown playing with a glass paperweight that serves as a prism or lens, allowing her to perceive objects or surfaces that do not exist or cannot be seen explicitly.

In Margarita with a Straw as well, the focus on Khanum’s use of wearable accessories and applying makeup, as well as Laila’s use of a swivel spoon and her augmentative alternative communication device, draws attention to the challenges that people with disabilities face when participating in various daily and leisure activities like playing musical instruments, choosing clothing, and using particular types of make-up products, utensils, and cutlery. Both the films (Barfi! and Margarita with a Straw), in some cases, create significant concerns: What is a ‘routine’ day-to-day activity? What activities may be classified as ‘day-to-day’? Who makes the decision? How? Is there a time and space limit for this kind of activity? Both attorneys and victims of handicap prejudice in India are frequently confronted with these complex concerns. When films address it using particular cinematic tactics and fictional tales, they bring these issues to the forefront and into public debate.

In the movie Main Aisa Hi Hoon, Indraneel fights to control his daughter. Because of the inherent apathetic attitude and stigma, Indraneel is about to lose the case, not because he is less capable of caring for his daughter. Instead, the role of the state and those in the various state apparatus and their no-ableist notion of thinking. Though here and there, the movie challenges the ableist notion of society, the end of it somehow establishes the hegemony of the ableist idea. The court granted custody to Indraneel after his advocate Niti married him and produced the marriage certificate in court. One way or the other way, the victory of Indraneel to take custody of his daughter is nothing but the victory of the ableist ideology of society, especially the way the case turns up at the end of the movie.

Nevertheless, there are other two films, i.e., Iqbal (Kukunoor, 2005) and Black (Bhansali, 2005), that challenge the ablest idea of society and bring a new perspective. In the movie Iqbal, Iqbal, a ‘deaf and mute boy who inspired to be a cricket player, faces an acute challenge from both his father and society at large. In his initial phase, the only solace for him is that his mother and sister are die-hard supporters of his cause or dream. He lived up to his dream and finally got selected for the Indian cricket team after defeating every hurdle thrown at him by society. He champions because of the environment created by his sister and coach Mohit, a drunkard but formerly a state champion. Putting the whole concept of the movie into a sentence; if a conducive environment is given to a ‘persons with disability’, s/he can defy the inherent ableist notion of society and can achieve their goal and set an example to society. Another movie, Black, has many facets to it. It is a highly complex movie giving interpretations like child abuse, to mould to live a ‘normal’, and many other facets. However, the movie’s undertone also has the same lines as Iqbal, Taare Zameen Par and Apna Aasmaan. The storyline of Black revolves around Michelle McNally, a deaf and blind girl. Though Hellen Keller inspired the story, the movie itself revealed so many facets of what a ‘person with disability’ goes through in their everyday life.

To conclude this chapter, cinema is one of the essential representational mediums and plays a very crucial role in presenting various social realities on the screen. As cinema in general, and Hindi film in particular has a large audience and a significant global reach, it is essential to examine the nuances of its operation and appreciate its ideological implications and the hegemonic discourse of ableism within which it exists. Responding to cinematic images of specific problems that arise in specific times and locations that influence the way experiences of disability are theorized, experienced, and lived may be more beneficial.

NOTES

1. Though there is not much difference between cinema and television regarding technology and production, there are still some minor differences. A film is more shoot days than a similar number of television pages. In a film stage, ‘two people talking’ is shot with motion and dynamics cameras, whereas a couple of static cameras handle/capture it on television. Further, television creates an innovative story and production, but films depend on or develop their retelling of stories,

2. For more details, see Matsuda et al., 1993; van Dijk, 1993, 1996; Whillock & Slayden, 1995; Riggins, 1997; Butler, 1998.

3. In Indian cuisine, fried puff-pastry balls filled with spiced mashed potato or chickpeas curry, spiced water, and tamarind juice.

4. ‘Aai’ refers to an informal way of addressing one’s mother in Hindi and Marathi languages. The abbreviated form of bisexual ‘bi’ seems to have been used to highlight an exciting wordplay and correlate with ‘bai’ (pronounced as bi), meaning servant in Hindi and Marathi.

REFERENCES

Bahadur, S. (1978). ‘The Context of Indian Film Culture’, Film Appreciation Study Material, Series No. 2, National Film Archives of India.

Bazin, A. (2009). ‘The Ontology of the Photographic Image.’ In Braudy and Cohen, Film Theory and Criticism, New Delhi: Oxford University Press.

Carroll, N. (1988a). Philosophical Problems of Classical Film Theory. Princeton: Princeton University Press.

——. (1988b). Mystifying Movies: Fads and Fallacies in Contemporary Film Theory. New York: Columbia University Press.

——. (1996a). Theorizing the Moving Image. New York: Cambridge University Press.

——. (1996b). ‘Prospects for film theory: a personal assessment’, in David Bordwell and Noel Carroll (eds.). Post-Theory: Reconstructing Film Studies. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press.

Corbett, E.P.J., and Connors, R.J. (1999). Classical Rhetoric for the Modern Student. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Cherney, J.L. (2011). ‘The Rhetoric of Ablesism’. Disability Studies Quarterly. Ohio State University.

Dayal, S. (2015). Dream Machine: Realism and Fantasy in Hindi Cinema. Philadelphia: Temple University Press.

Elsaesser, T. and Buckland, W. (2002). Studying Contemporary American Film. Arnold. Member of the Hodder Headline Group, London.

Falzon, F. (2007). Philosophy Goes to the Movies: An Introduction to Philosophy. New York: Routledge.

Fraser, B. (ed.). (2016). Cultures of Representation: Disability in World Cinema Contexts, New York: Columbia University Press.

Ghosh, S. (2016). Dunce! Duffer! Dimwit! Dyslexia in Bollywood’s Taare Zameen Par (2007) in Benjamin Frase (ed.), Cultures of Representation Disability in World Cinema Contexts, New York: Columbia University Press.

Giannetti, L. (2017). Understanding Movies. Pearson.

Juluri, V. (2013). Bollywood Nation: India Through its Cinema, New Delhi: Penguin Books India.

Lal, V. and Nandy, A. (ed.) (2016). Fingerprinting Popular Culture: The Mythic and the Iconic in Indian Cinema. New Delhi: Oxford University Press.

Metz, C. (1974). Film Language: A Semiotics of the Cinema, tr. Michael Taylor, New York: Oxford University Press.

Metz, C. (1982). Psychoanalysis and Cinema: The Imaginary Signifier, London: Macmillan.

Mitchell, D.T. and Snyder, S.L. (2015). The Biopolitics of Disability: Neoliberalism, Ablenationalism, and Peripheral Embodiment. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor.

——. (2016). ‘Global In(ter)dependent Disability Cinema Targeting Ephemeral Domains of Belief and Cultivating Aficionados of the Body’, In Benjamin Frase (ed.), Cultures of Representation Disability in World Cinema Contexts. New York: Columbia University Press.

Nandy, A. (ed.) (1998). The Secret Politics of Our Desires: Innocence, Culpability and Indian Popular Cinema. New Delhi and New York: Oxford University Press.

Norden, M.F. (1994). The Cinema of Isolation: A History of Physical Disability in the Movies. New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press.

Peirce, C.S. (1955). Philosophical Writings of Peirce. Edited by Justus Buchler. New York: Dover.

Powdermaker, H. (1947). ‘An Anthropologist Looks at the Movies’, Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, pp. 80-7, quoted in J.S.R. Goodlad, A Sociology of Popular Drama, Heinemann, London, 1971, p. 3.

Rajadhyaksha, A. (2016). Indian Cinema: A Very Short Introduction. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Siebers, T. (2006). ‘Disability in Theory From Social Constructionism to the New Realism of the Body’, in Lennard J. Davis (ed.), The Disability Studies Reader, 2nd edn., New York: Routledge.

Tremain, S. (2006). ‘On the Government of Disability: Foucault, Power, and the Subject of Impairment’, in Lennard J. Davis (ed.), The Disability Studies Reader, 2nd edn., New York: Routledge.

Trent, J. (1984). Inventing the Feeble Mind: A History of Mental Retardation in the United States.

Vasudevan, R. (2010). The Melodramatic Public: Film Form and Spectatorship in Indian Cinema. New Delhi: Permanent Black.

Virdi, J. (2003). The Cinematic Imagination: Indian Popular Films as Social History. New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, New Delhi: Permanent Black.

CHAPTER 5

Epistemic Ashrāfiya-Morality and
Urdu Theatre Public Sphere in
Nineteenth-Century Bihar
Muslim Internal-Decoloniality*

NESHAT QUAISER

…throw this enemy-of-morality-civility-and-faith woman immediately out of this theatre Company (Al-Punch, 1891, 7/15).

Lots of lowly people, very few highborn [in theatre hall] (Al-Punch, 1898, 14/39).

INTRODUCTION

This chapter attempts to provide a Muslim internal decolonial critique of the hegemonic ashrāfiya1 knowledge-oligarchies. Epistemic ashrāfiya-morality is produced by these oligarchies as a mechanism to colonise the shudra2-dalit3-disenfranchised Muslim mind internally. Through the prism of the Western style Urdu theatre in the last quarter of the nineteenth century in the Indian province of Bihar, this essay examines the epistemic ashrāfiya-morality-based responses to the popularity of the Western-style theatre and its ‘corrupting influences’; participation of the ‘lowly’ women and men in theatre that posed a threat to ashrāfiya-moral order; a possible subaltern counter-intuitive subjectivity; women as objects of marketized desire and other related issues. Although the essay deals with the colonial period, it has theoretical implications for comprehending the convincing continuity of epistemic ashrāfiya-morality in the postcolonial Indian subcontinent.

The essay, divided into four sections, draws primarily on Urdu weekly Al-Punch.4 Section I outlines the concepts of epistemic ashrāfiya-morality; Muslim internal-decoloniality; ashrāf; and ashrāfiya-morality. Section II provides a brief overview of Urdu theatre in the late nineteenth century Bihar. Section III, with three sub-sections, deals with the questions of popularity; contending moralities; responses to the ‘morally corrupting’ theatre; subaltern counter-intuitive subjectivity; ‘lowly’ subalterns in theatre posing a threat to ashrāfiya moral order; maghribyat5 (Westernism) and ashrāfiya’s responses to colonialism; spatial-cultural, urban-suburban and ashrāfiya-subaltern tensions; and the ‘lowly’-bāzāri7 women as objects of disdain and desire. Section IV, the conclusion, outlines the Urdu theatre public sphere; the historicity of the epistemic ashrāfiya-morality; and ashrāfiya’s umma7-making endeavours and colonising the mind internally.

Section I: Epistemic Ashrāfiya-Morality and
Muslim Internal-Decoloniality

Morality denotes a normative framework determining human transactions in different forms in all the fields of social life (for general concepts of morality, see Carson: 1984; Harmen: 1977). However, morality is inscribed in ideologies of caste, class, race, religion, and culture; thereby, we find contending conceptions of morality (for contending moralities in our context see, Section III). But when morality is epistemically foregrounded as a religious-universal moral prescription, it becomes a ‘choreographically occultating’ ideology. Thus, epistemic ashrāfiya-morality is that which claims non-ashrāf morality and ethics cannot be authentic. It works from the logic that authentic morality that guides all-encompassing conduct in society derives from superior caste-class, and race/tribe and family lineages and it alone can produce true knowledge. Epistemic ashrāfiya-morality, therefore, excludes shudra-dalit Muslims from knowledge production. This supremacist moral framework produces relations of domination. Thus, epistemically privileged ashrāfiya-morality was/is presented as an authentic Islamic general moral framework that aimed to colonize the non-ashrāf Muslim mind. Epistemic ashrāfiya-morality is produced by the internal hegemonic ashrāfiya knowledge-oligarchies. This calls for decolonizing the Muslim mind internally.

In the context of colonialism, decolonizing refers to deconstructing the social, cultural, and political thoughts and values radiating from the colonial/western/white centres of power (for the concept of decolonization/decoloniality (see Thiong’o: 1986; Fanon: 2001; Mignolo & Walsh: 2018). Muslim decoloniality primarily focused on Western colonial technologies of domination to reshape and mould Islam and Muslim societies by privileging the Western/ ‘modern’/orientalist constructions of religion and Islam, where secularism, democracy, and modernity emerged as the defining concepts. This engendered different Muslim counter-perspectives. Muslim decolonial thinking, however, as a part of a widely desired counter-strategy, pre-dominantly deployed arguments such as Islam is, by its very nature, modern, democratic and a harbinger of peace, etc.; and that Muslims are Ummat-e-Wasa_t, meaning that Muslims are just, away from extremism, undogmatic, and ‘moderate’. However, concepts such as Al-zarūrāt tobīh al-mahzūrāt (necessities permit impermissible things), i]ztirārī (despairing) conditions, and istishhād (desired death of a martyr) have also come into play. Muslim decolonial thinking also meant critiquing epistemological and ontological foundations of European Enlightenment, reason, secularism, and modernity, to develop a Muslim/Islamic intellectual counter-strategy (for Muslim decoloniality, see among others (Wali Allah: 1995; Al-Attas: 1993; Asad: 1993; Sayyid: 2014).

The overriding theoretical thrust of the grand Muslim decoloniality has been to consider Islam as an internally cohesive and universal religion, in which ‘political’ compulsions also played a significant role, and considering Muslims as textually-driven non-hierarchized essentialist category, with the notion of umma as the underlying structuring principle. This may be called the ashrāfiya oligarchic Muslim decoloniality, as the external-colonial-factors-driven Muslim decoloniality has expediently not paid the required critical attention to the following crucial issues from the internal-decoloniality perspective: Islamic ‘canonical tensions and contradictions’; the manipulative maslaki8-jurisprudential hegemony; caste-race-lineage-class-based theories and practices of discrimination among the Muslims; and the ashrāfiya internal ‘epistemic’ and corporal violence. A critical examination of these issues alone will be able to unpack the colonizing the mind projects of the hegemonic ashrāfiya knowledge-oligarchies within Islamic/Muslim states, societies, religion and politics. Therefore, Muslim internal-decoloniality denotes shifting ontologically the focus from external to internal, within the wider historical and intellectual contexts, without necessarily neglecting the epistemic foundations of external colonial experiences. Muslim internal-decoloniality assumes greater significance as the continuation of epistemic ashrāfiya-morality has acquired newer implications not only in the Indian subcontinent but also for other Muslim societies as well.

Ashrāf and Ashrāfiya-Morality

Ashrāf (plural of sharīf—of noble birth) are considered to be those Muslims who claimed to be of foreign origin with highborn lineages such as Sayyed (supposed to be descendants of the Prophet), shaikh (supposed to be descendants of Prophet’s companions), and Mughal and Pathan. We have learned to take this ashrāf-propelled self-representation for an unquestionable truth.9 Such claims remain unsubstantiated in the case of most members of these categories in the Indian subcontinent. However, the early ashrāf—since very long disconnected from their foreign locales of origin—along with the later incorporated members of local origin constituted a hegemonic ashrāfiya-oligarchy. They derived their distinctiveness akin to savarna (high-caste Hindus) from their claims to be of noble birth. The only expedient model available to them was the Hindu ascriptive caste hierarchical model, which could enable them to maintain their high social status due to their claims to be of noble birth of foreign origin, which would distinguish them from the shudra-dalit Indian Muslims. Ashrāf’s claims of high status, as preordained, corresponded to the Hindu ideology of ascriptive status for justifying social segregation between savarna and shudra-dalit. Marriages with shudra-dalit Muslim castes are disdained, as it ‘polluted’ the ‘purity’.

Thus, the caste system among Muslims in the Indian subcontinent contains the Hindu caste constitutive features like endogamy, mandatory segregation based on ascriptive occupational affiliation, status hierarchy, and also ritual purity and pollution with varying regional differences, but only in overt expression as these have expediently been equated with Islamic notions of ‘pāk’ (clean) and ‘nāpāk’ (unclean) (for caste among the Muslims, see Ansari: 1960; Momin: 1977; Sachar Committee Report, 2006; Ranganath Misra Commission Report, 2007; P. S. Krishnan Report, 2007; Deshpande, 2008). However, some scholars have argued that the caste system among Muslims differs from the Hindu model (Ahmad: 1973; Dumont: 1980). However empirical evidence suggest that the causal relationship between a Muslim’s caste location and her/his related social disabilities are in no way different from the Hindu caste practices, which are continually reproduced (Quaiser: 2011, 49-68; Anwar: 2005; Rā‘īn: 2013; Trivedi et al., 2016, 32-6; Lee: 2018, 1-27).

Charles Lindholm (1995, 449-67) has insightfully discussed various approaches on caste among Muslims in India such as structural-functionalist adaptive, normative, essentialist, reflective symbolic, interpretative/constructionist, comparative, diffusionist, and indigenous monistic. The discussion shows a great deal of confusion, chaos, and conflicting oscillation in comprehending caste among Muslims in the Indian subcontinent. These approaches predominantly consider the ashrāf-ajlāf-arzāl divisions in terms of ‘adaptive’ practices, not in terms of palpable ‘caste’ divisions among Muslims as concretized in India defying even Islamic textual equality and justice. Ashrāf adopted an adaptive-essentialist strategy and portrayed the adaptive elements from the Hindu caste system as Islamic-essentialist in their exclusionary relations with shudra-dalit Muslims, in which ashrāfiya ‘ulama (scholars of Islam) crucially contributed. This lived reality has produced hegemonic casteist ashrāfiya subjectivity.

Epistemic ashrāfiya-morality, as a mechanism to colonize the mind, emanated from the ashrāf-propelled self-representation and the Hindu caste structures. There were/are four principal constitutive elements of this moral order: firstly, expediently reinterpreted10 subcontinental maslaki-jurisprudential notions of Islamic moral values11 to the advantage of ashrāfiya; secondly, pride in original Arab, Iranian and Central-Asian lineages and entrenchment in the Hindu caste system that enabled ashrāfiya to assume a superior ascriptive position akin to savarna; thirdly, pride in the subcontinental conquistador lineages; and fourthly, ashrāfiya’s collaboration with colonialism and other structures of oppression to safeguard their privileges after the final fall of ashrāfiya political power in 1857. The processes of the formation of this epistemic ashrāfiya-morality had begun with newer dimensions since the second half of the eighteenth century. This propelled them to engage vigorously in umma-making endeavours in the given contexts (see Section IV below). Equipped with these mechanisms of colonizing the mind, ashrāfiya foregrounded the epistemic morality almost as divine predestination to reproduce conforming shudra-dalit Muslim subjects.

It was against this backdrop that the ashrāfiya’s morality-related anxieties and dilemmas in the wake of colonialism produced Urdu akhlāq literature (morality-related literature) in South Asia since the late nineteenth century, which ranged from philosophical debate to issues of everyday life. Akhlāq literature ultimately represented not only ashrāfiya’s moral dilemmas but also their quest for a ‘modern’ Muslim identity in colonial India with a new ‘liberal’ Islamic identity, which ultimately set the tone for a new akhlāqiyāt (moral code). This ultimately produced a reconciled ‘mixture’ of expediently ashrāfiya-reinterpreted Islamic moral values and western-colonial moral norms, revealing the two-facedness of the epistemic ashrāfiya-morality (for Urdu akhlāq and adab literature representing dominant ashrāfiya-morality, see Alam: 2004; Pernau: 2017, 21-42; Metcalf: 1984; Hasan: 2007).

Section II: Urdu Theatre in Bihar:
A Brief Overview

This section presents a brief account of Urdu theatre in nineteenth-century Bihar. We find that the theatre that the ashrāfiya opposed for its ‘corrupting influences’ was simultaneously patronized by them. Thus, ashrāfiya’s reconciliation was stronger than the ambiguities.

The introduction of Western-style stage theatre in nineteenth century India emerged not only as a site to legitimise colonial rule but also to contest it. However, beyond this binary, the theatre also became a site to contest local caste-class-race-religion-based ideologies of domination, particularly in terms of subalterns’ participation. The new theatre had come into existence in Calcutta in 1831, but it began in a big way after 1857. Theatre emerged as a potent site where the colonial rule, western/colonial modernity, existing institutions and moralities, and different responses to these came to be debated that created a theatre public sphere (for theatre in colonial India, see Bhatia, 2008; Singh, 2010).

The history of ‘modern’ Urdu theatre began with the Indar Sabha of Amānat Lakhnavi which was staged in Lucknow in the early 1850s. However, it was after 1857 that professional theatrical companies were established on commercial lines mostly by Pārsīs (Zoroastrians). After the initial success in staging Gujrāti plays, Pārsīs took to commercially most promising Urdu plays, and a new phase of competitive theatre began (for Urdu theatre, see Nāmi: 1962; Rahmāni: 1987; Hansen: 2003, 381-405; Hansen, 2016, 1-30). Professional actors, singers, musicians, playwrights, costume designers, and importantly female actors were introduced. They expanded their activities beyond Bombay and staged Urdu plays in several Indian cities and towns, attaining popularity.

In Bihar, two Urdu plays—Sajjād wa Sumbul and Shamshād wa Sausan were written in 1874 (Hasan: 1959, 33-8) by K.R. Bhatt12 which were seemingly influenced by some Bangla plays. However, it was in the year 1884 that a theatre company called Imperial Theatrical Troupe staged several plays in Patna which became popular (‘Abdulwadūd: 1952). Soon after, Bihar Theatrical Troupe was established in Patna (Hasan: 1959, 8-13). In 1891, the arrival of Jubilee Theatrical Company in Patna was reported, but was explicitly unwelcome:

In the month of February, this Company came to our city and staged several plays. With God’s blessings…now it is planning to move towards the west. (Al-Punch, 1891, 7/15).

In 1892, Dam_rī Mukhtār Ka Theatre (Dam_rī Mukhtār’s Theatre) was founded. This theatre company staged plays in and outside Patna and gained popularity. This was a professional company in which not only male but also female actors worked, and they were paid a proper salary. This company’s well-known male and female actors were Mahbūb, Jawāhar, Khurshīd, Nasīr, and Nādir, of which Mahbūb and Jawāhar were very famous. Mahbūb excelled in his zenāna roles, and theatre halls were always full to watch him act (Hasan: 1959, 11-14). Nasīr too performed zenāna roles, and in the play Zahr-e Ishq,13 he played the role of Māhjabīn (Al-Punch, 1892, 8/14).14 Dam_rī Mukhtār Theatre usually staged Urdu plays which were already popular such as Zahr-e Ishq, Indar Sabha, Harish Chandar and Gul Bakauli. In addition to Patna, it staged plays in several other cities and towns, such as Gaya (ibid.) and Muzaffarpūr (Hasan: 1959, 11-14) and every year in the famous Sonepūr fair (Hasan: 1959, 8-13). When Dam_rī Mukhtār’s Theatre became popular and attracted particularly students in large numbers, it was more vigorously opposed. It finally packed up, and its exit was celebrated:

Boys have stopped going to theatre, and public has developed hatred…due to lack of patronage from schoolboys, Dam_rī Theatre’s sources of income have shrunk (Al-Punch, 1892, 8/2).

After a gap of about five years, Dam_rī Theatre was reorganized in 1898 as Bihar Theatrical Company in Patna City, with a stage in Bānkīpūr15 as well. Mahbūb of Dam_rī Theatre fame joined this company and became its star actor. The company’s actress Bismillah attracted young people in large numbers. ‘Students again came back to the theatre and once again, a theatre ripple was created’ (Hasan: 1959, 8-13). Opposition to the theatre resumed, but the Company continued to stage plays (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/18). Bihar Theatrical Company staged several popular plays, such as Āshiq-e Jāñbāz, Zahr-e Ishq, Indar Sabha, Katora-Bhar Khūn, Dorangi Dunya, Dhūp Čhāon, Asīr-e Hawas, Khūbsūrat Balā, etc. As a result of its success, several professional and amateur theatre companies were formed in early twentieth century that continued for some time (Hasan: 1959, 11-14). Most of these plays were based on traditional masnavi (long narrative poem), dāstān (oral storytelling), qissa (tales), etc., or were an adaptation of English plays. The central themes of these plays mostly related to love stories and heroic deeds. They reinforced mostly the epistemic ashrāfiya-moral values.

Section III: Popularity, ‘Corrupting Influences’, ‘Lowly’
Women and Men, Spatial-Cultural Tensions, Contending
Moralities and Counter-Intuitive Subjectivity

This section, in addition to an introduction, is divided into three subsections: (a) The popularity of the theatre and its ‘corrupting influences’; (b) The Bānkīpūr argument: modernist response, spatial-cultural, urban-suburban and subaltern-ashrāfiya, tensions; and (c) ‘lowly’-bāzāri women: disdain and marketized desire.

Urdu theatre performances, spectators, stage, actors, theatre companies, ashrāfiya, literate public, ‘lowly’ women and men, and students, with multiple familiar and unfamiliar issues and questions, created an Urdu theatre public sphere16 (see Section IV) in which ‘epistemic ashrāfiya-morality and subalterns’17 participation were the key organizing principles.

Since the 1870s theatre in Bihar attracted not only the ashrāfiya, emerging educated and professional middle classes, but also the ‘lowly’ women and men. Theatre ka tamāsha dekhna (to watch theatre performance) was emerging as a critical supplementary source to form new identities in the colonial contexts. However, the active participation of the subalterns deeply disturbed the ashrāfiya moral-cultural order. Thus, the expedient ashrāfiya opposition to the popularity of theatre among the masses (‘awām-commoners, bāzāri women, shudras, students) was an attempt to pre-empt a possible subaltern ideological challenge.

The participation, responses, and the role of ‘awām, shudra Muslims, ‘bāzārī’ women about theatre were neither ‘written’ by themselves nor were adequately recorded in the newspapers or elsewhere in their voice. Evidence of critical subaltern participation is to be extracted even from the disdainful ashrāfiya narratives. Thus, ironically, they registered their presence through antagonistic and disdainful representations in ashrāfiya narratives, thus, the absence was turned into presence, subverting the very logic of that narrative, as is evident from what follows.

However, how would subalterns possibly gain counter-intuitive subjectivity from the plays, which did not at all relate to subalterns’ life conditions, and which reinforced ashrāfiya moral values? In most of the plays, the subalterns patronized so eagerly in different ways, were based on traditional tales or an adaptation from English plays with highborn as central characters, and which were deeply entrenched in epistemic ashrāfiya moral values. Yes, but the very fact that the subalterns came out of their socially assigned places of exclusion and entered the hitherto exclusive ashrāfiya spaces publicly was of critical importance. While doing so, subalterns defied the charted process of expected subject formation18 and refused to be constituted expectedly by the ashrāfiya moral authority. The active participation of ‘lowly’ women and men in theatre signified the formation of a counter-intuitive subjectivity, no matter in what embryonic form it may have been. The acts of being spectators and actors formed a critical constitutive element of a new subject formation, as the subalterns were excluded from the domain of knowledge in print. The very fact that the ashrāfiya launched a tirade against subalterns’ participation in theatre provided internal evidence of their critical presence and a possible counter-intuitive subject formation. This counter-intuitive subject formation was not premeditated, and yet not unintended (see concluding remarks in this section). Besides this, theatre, despite having colonial connotations, facilitated subalterns’ public visibility in exclusive ashrāfiya social spaces (for how subalterns gained from British presence, see Guru: 2005).

Thus, there emerged three sets of contending moralities: firstly, two-faced epistemic ashrāfiya-morality; secondly, subaltern morality, which was constituted by the very act of subalterns’ participation in theatre that had a promise of a counter-intuitive subjectivity, even if the contents of the plays were not subaltern-centric. This, in essence, was an act in defiance of the ashrāfiya prescribed moral codes of quiescence, passivity, and submission. The act of viewing theatre was a critical constitutive element for a new subaltern moral imagination, as knowledge in print was not their prerogative; thirdly, a colonial moral regime in a sense supported ashrāfiya-morality, yet theatre created an atmosphere for recognizable social visibility of subaltern ‘bāzārī’ women and ‘lowly’ men, ironically though.

(a) Popularity of the theatre and ‘corrupting influences’

The popularity of theatre and concerns for its ‘corrupting influences’ assumed specific ideological connotations. Popularity simultaneously entails inclusionary and exclusionary connotations. In the given context, however, ‘popular’ tended to emerge as the early colonial populism for appealing to the colonized of all categories including ordinary people to legitimize colonial ideological apparatuses. This was different from ‘authoritarian populism’ where ‘the people’ are pitted against the elite as Stuart Hall had enunciated in the late 1970s;19 but beneath-the-surface logic common to both is to produce homogeneousness through explicit or implicit pressure. These characteristics were at play in the debate on theatre, under discussion, in different forms. Ashrāfiya’s responses were exclusionary as they targeted mainly ‘lowly’ people to make theatre popular, engendering defiance. Students of ashrāfiya stock were deplored as they not only defied paternal authority, for visiting theatre meant knowing and imbibing new ideas, but also for they would ruin their chances of a bright future in the colonial administration by wasting their time in theatre.

We shall now briefly illustrate ashrāfiya responses to the popularity of theatre and its ‘corrupting influence’.

A newspaper in early 1885 reported that a theatre company staged several plays last year and gained immense popularity. It commented:

Inhabitants of proper Patna are fully aware of the Imperial Theatrical Troupe… its plays had captivated not only the rich, nobles, different occupational categories, public in general but also the students… last year, the Imperial Theatrical Troupe’s plays ruthlessly impacted the education and good conduct of our able and innocent students (‘Abdulwadūd: 1952; Hasan: 1959, 8-13).

Theatre’s popularity had captivated also the educated middle-ashrāfiya professionals such as lawyers that disturbed the high-ashrāfiya. Lamenting the extent of theatre’s adverse impact on lawyers and students, a report much later observed:

Now listen to the kind of impact theatre had on rich and powerful, lawyers and students. Keeping aside their valuable legal works, and slate and books… they reached the theatre hall as the clock struck seven o’clock (evening) (Al-Punch, 1892, 8/14).

One Nasserul-zurafa’ in a letter to the editor sarcastically suggested making use of theatre to tackle the cholera epidemic:

Theatre is next to college… ask Mahbūb to sing in his characteristic style, and you will see Haiza (cholera) Khan would run away. (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/33).

The suggestion conveyed the message that theatre is so lethal that even cholera would run away on seeing it. The reference to Haiza ‘Khan’ has a subcontinental Muslim conquistador connotation that even great Pathan and Mughal warriors would run away in the face of the morally corrupting armoury of theatre. And yet one cannot miss in it the elements of appreciation of theatre.

In the face of upsetting tensions produced by the popularity of the theatre, some ashrāfiya thought of using theatre to reform the qaum (community/Muslim community) and society. One Sayyed Mohammad Nawāb Mohammad wrote a play Jawan-Bakht wa Shamsunnahār (Mohammad: 1884) for reforming the qaum, because plays staged by theatre companies were not morally fit for the cultured and educated society. A similar concern was expressed in the face of ‘moral degradation’ caused by ‘lowly’ women in the theatre in which the references to qaum and ‘our Muslim brothers’ assumed significant connotations:

Jubilee Theatrical Company has publicized itself with magnified honourable claims as sympathiser of the country and qaum, and educator of morality. But these claims are misplaced. It has presented a wanton-eyed woman on the stage. Some people sympathise with this Company, for it is established by … our Muslim brothers. My suggestion is: throw this … woman immediately out of the Company (Al-Punch, 1891, 7/15).

Therefore, ‘reform’ within the qaum was essentially an ashrāfiya concern for self-preservation.

Corrupting influence of theatre on students and young was opposed by both ‘modernist’ and ‘traditionalist’ ashrāfiya. The traditionalist response was more concerned with the growing erosion of traditional Islamic moral values, expressed in the language of anti-maghribyat. A very prominent ashrāfiya Urdu writer and poet, Maulana Fazl-e Haq Āzād ‘Azīmābādī20 wrote:

If possible, approach the Lieutenant Governor that he should try to remove prostitutes and theatre from India. These are corrupting the morals of people. And also, the influx of European novels in India should be prohibited because in them such materials are that the poetry of Jān Sāheb21 would appear like a dry leaf… (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/5).

Although Āzād expressed his concerns strongly for the preservation of Islamic values and protecting Indians from European culture, novels, prostitutes, and the corrupting influences of theatre, he merely appealed to the Governor rather politely. This is for, despite his strong opposition to the theatre, Āzād was very much in favour of Muslims and others acquiring Western knowledge and considered British rule as a boon for India. He was perhaps making a distinction between Western culture and Western scientific inventions and colonial administration.

This concern found expression in different forms, including English education for Indian girls. In a letter to the editor, one M. M. Sokhtadil wrote:

How the girls of respectable people would on a khatolī (a small bedstead) go to school and learn the lesson of a, b, c. This much one can tolerate. But after this, our simpleton girls of Bihar would shake hands with memsahib, which means after completing education they will fight with their husbands for freedom. So, our Bihar is going the London way (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/10).

Sokhtadil, though hesitant about English education for respectable ashrāfiya girls outside the home, is ready to tolerate ‘up to this’, revealing a gradual acceptance of English education even for girls. But he expressed a grave concern relating to the control over women’s bodies, sexuality, and expectations for strict adherence to the assigned religious-cultural roles of a wife.22 Coming in contact with memsahib would morally contaminate the girls, as it would encourage them to deviate from the well-defined normative roles of an obedient wife.

Modernist response to the popularity of the theatre and its corrupting influences is discussed in the following subsection, as it is entangled with other emerging complex issues whereby epistemic ashrāfiya-morality was acquiring newer characteristics.

(b) The Bānkīpūr Argument: Modernist Response, Spatial-Cultural, Urban-Suburban and Subaltern-Ashrāfiya Tensions

Modernist response to the theatre was entangled with more compelling and complex emerging issues. Most ashrāfiya tended to be ‘modernist’ and were aligned with the colonial power adding new dimensions to epistemic ashrāfiya-morality. Theatre, subalterns’ recognizable social visibility, colonial modernity, English education, colonial administration, etc. produced tensions of all kinds within the emerging modernist ashrāfiya. These tensions were reflected through theatre in different forms, such as the tensions between the ‘modern’ and the old-fashioned residential localities; between the ashrāfiya and subalterns; and between the urban (shahri) and suburban (qasbāti) ashrāfiya. These tensions reflected conflicting economic, social, and political interests of urban and suburban ashrāfiya and the subalterns. The following report reveals the theatre-related tensions and the reference to qaum in it denoted ashrāfiya:

When theatre comes to Bānkīpūr, school children come under the control of some jinn. We heard it with great sorrow that a student of T.K. Ghosh Academy…with some boys of Patna Collegiate has taken contract of theatre, which has saddened us most. Surprisingly, why did our kind and noble Headmaster of Patna Collegiate, Moulvi Amjad Ali Saheb not take corrective measures? If he takes little interest…these boys can be reformed… and qaum would thank him (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/33).

One Kammo, in a letter, expressed similar concern for qaum’s welfare regarding the hostility between modern and traditional localities that theatre had produced, threatening even physical violence:

…you keep unravelling political knots, how would you know the evil doings of theatre. You could not even ask why, leaving the whole of Patna,23 has it come to Bānkīpūr? And why does it choose a place...just opposite Patna College? If you have even an iota of interest in qaum’s welfare, you should stop them…. They should at least leave Bānkīpūr and perform their jugglery and rope-dancing in Patna and make money. If you cannot do it yourself, order your followers to tear them into pieces. Otherwise, I am ready to take on them (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/18).

The above report and the letter reveal an emerging conflict between the westernizing Bānkīpūr and the old medieval Patna City. Bānkīpūr is a neighbourhood and residential area in Patna. Until the early twentieth century, Bānkīpūr was the administrative centre of the Patna Division of Bihar, which came under the rule of the British East India Company following the battle of Buxar in 1764. Bānkīpūr, since the 1860s, signified a ‘modern’ locality inhabited by modern-oriented people. It was in Bānkīpūr where English medium educational institutions, new architecture, modern markets, Western dress, Bānkīpūr Club, Bihar Young Men’s Institute, Jahangir’s Theatre and Cinema Hall, Rammohun Roy Seminary (an English Medium High School), Patna Collegiate, etc. existed. These were the markers of modernity. English medium education, colonial power, and new job opportunities attracted the traditional urban-suburban high-ashrāfiya and other emerging English educated middle-ashrāfiya and other middle classes.

The argument in Kammo’s above-mentioned letter that theatre should leave Bānkīpūr and perform in Patna City signified tensions within the new ashrāfiya, emanating from two main concerns: firstly, to sustain the hold of epistemic ashrāfiya moral codes over the ‘lowly’ people by keeping them away from Bānkīpūr. Patna City was predominantly inhabited by subalterns, labouring poor, artisans, shudra-dalit Muslims and Hindus—the non-ashrāf population. The underlying argument was that there was no problem if theatre was performed in the old City as people in that locality were outdated, incapable of upward social mobility and it was preordained that they were born poor and low in the caste hierarchy. If they come to Bānkīpūr to watch theatre, a culture of subaltern defiance will grow here as well. Secondly, the concern that theatre was distracting their progenies from being studious and competitive, a necessity for acquiring ‘respectable’ jobs in the colonial administration, which would bring additional enviable social esteem. Thus, Bānkīpūr emerged as a site for new social, educational and economic opportunities from which ashrāfiya alone were to benefit. Ashrāfiya, thus, actively collaborated with the colonial administration in all possible ways. For example, despite their claim to be ‘modern’, ashrāfiya were critical of the ‘corrupting influence’ of the theatre for reasons of political expediency as well. It enabled them to emerge as the sole representative of ‘Muslim’/Islamic/Indian/Eastern moral values and culture in the eyes of colonial administration. They became the representative of ‘the community’s (all Muslims’) interest’. This became evident when ashrāfiya hugely benefitted from the separate electorate (Vohra: 2001, 113-15). In the process, ashrāfiya acquired jobs and positions of power in the colonial administration, educational institutions, and judiciary, and benefitted from the newly emerging political process.

Bānkīpūr and theatre also signified tensions between the urban and suburban ashrāfiya, in which conflicting cultural, economic, and political interests were palpable. After 1857, both the urban (shahri) and suburban (qasbāti) ashrāfiya began to move to Bānkīpūr. But the conflict between the two was expressed through culture, language and literature. City-bred urbane high ashrāfiya of Patna City were high-caste traditionally landed, affluent, and pedigreed nobles, having urban-traditional education. The suburban ashrāfiya were high-caste landed gentry of respectable families with suburban-traditional education and constituted the suburban aristocracy. But the Patna City-based urbane ashrāfiya considered themselves of high culture and refined manners, and a repository of high linguistic and literary traditions. They considered the suburban ashrāfiya rustic in their manners and substandard in matters of language, accent and literature. Their suburban location of origin rendered them culturally inferior in the eyes of the city-bred ashrāfiya. This produced a bitter tiff between the two. They launched a diatribe against each other to prove their cultural and literary superiority, and the theatre did not remain unaffected by this, and for which Al-Punch provided space liberally.

Nonetheless, even such acrimonious argumentativeness contributed significantly to the emergence of a culture of critical public debate enriching comprehension not only of language and literature but also of politics, colonial rule, English education, and other issues. However, suburban ashrāfiya such as Fazl-e-Haq Āzād too had been well-informed of theatre and had strongly opposed it, and was considered to be the intellectual resource person behind Al-Punch. The editor and owner of Al-Punch too was a suburban ashrāfiya. They, too, could not resist the temptation of being part of the new centre of culture and economy and began to move to Bānkīpūr, with the view to getting their share in the land of new opportunities. And soon they did make their presence felt in Bānkīpūr in a big way. For example, the Imam family from the suburban Neora became perhaps the most prominent family of Bānkīpūr. Thus, Bānkīpūr emerged as a site for the making of a post-1857 ashrāfiya intellectual ethos.

By the end of the nineteenth century, ambiguities gave way to reconciliation and ashrāfiya began to accept the ‘morally corrupting’ theatre expediently. They took to the theatre to seek pleasure, with women emerging as objects of desire, as is evident from the following letter:

…brother, tell me, have you ever watched this theatre even in disguise…it is all pleasure and enjoyment… (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/18).

More forthright appreciation followed:

Bihar Theatrical Company staged its play Āshiq-e Jāñbāz very nicely, with spectators in large numbers. Mast Nāz’s style of acting…was wonderful… and why not…this role was performed by the old master Mahbūb (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/24).

However, ‘lowly’ men and women continued to be condemned by casteist disdain and blamed for the popularity of theatre, and ‘modern’ ashrāfiya had no difficulty in collaborating with the colonial apparatuses. For example, theatre brought ‘lowly’ people in close physical proximity to high and middle ashrāfiya, which amounted to breaking the boundaries of casteist segregation, despite seating segregation according to the price of tickets and social status. This produced an alarmist reaction. Thus, a weaver was disdainfully reminded of his ascriptive status:

Leaving his loom, he goes to the theatre. For no reason, he will be harmed. If this eagerness to visit the theatre continues, even his loom will be sold out (Al-Punch, 1906, 22/46).

The above reminder communicated the casteist social status of a shudra Muslim in the language of the patron-client relationship. A stern message was conveyed that stick to your ascribed occupation; do not aspire for any vertical mobility by changing your occupation or emulating ashrāfiya cultural practices; to watch theatre neglecting loom was not your job. Despite repeated admission that the theatre was patronized even by nobles, ashrāfiya educated people, lawyers and students, yet subalterns were blamed for the popularity of the morally corrupting theatre by lamenting that: ‘a lot of lowly people, very few highborn’ [in the theatre hall] (Al-Punch, 1898, 14/39).

(c) ‘Lowly’—‘Bāzārī’ Women: Disdain and Marketized Desire

Gender and sexuality are inscribed in caste class, religion, ethnicity, and nationality (with theatre, see Bhattacharya: 1998; Hansen: 1999, 127-47; Singh: 2010). Accordingly, a clear division existed between the subaltern and the upper-caste women about theatre under study. Theatre created an atmosphere for women to undertake a journey from home-shanty-kothā (kothā—broadly, a whorehouse) to public stage contesting differently the ashrāfiya notions of women’s moral virtues. For ‘decent’ women, the home was a well-guarded place where they could be kept under control. Their participation in theatre was largely a sign of relative freedom encouraged by ashrāfiya men, who were too eager to be a part of the colonial power structures. Caste-based hierarchized predispositions were clear, as sympathetic concerns were expressed in the case of respectable women. For example, a bit sarcastically but not disdainfully, it was expressed that now even women (here, decent ones) are attracted to the theatre:

Fair sex too now… have leanings for theatre

Listening to praises, they are restless with eagerness

Making tinkling sound of anklets, they come (Al-Punch, 1892, 8/1).

On the other hand, it is evident from the available sources that low-caste women, branded as ‘bāzārī’, entered the theatre as performers primarily to earn a livelihood.24 ‘Lowly-bāzārī’ theatre women were targeted for causing moral degradation; ashrāfiya believed that they could easily be consumed and owned as objects of desire. In a report, describing the caste-class composition of spectators in a theatre hall, a clear distinction was made between respectable chaste and ‘lowly’-bāzārī women and it was contemptuously stated that only with bāzārī women, one can act lasciviously. One Fakhrul-Zurafa Māel Dharampūrī Darbhangavi wrote:

They were respectable, chaste and pious wives and daughters of Bengali bābūs25…bāzārī women had not gone there, so there was no chance for you to act lasciviously (Al-Punch, 1898, 14/39).

Thus, the subaltern women were portrayed as of lax morals, and ashrāfiya demanded that the Theatre Company divest them of their means of livelihood. While doing so, upholders of the ashrāfiya-morality two-facedly described the same women lasciviously:26

It has presented a wanton-eyed, unceremonious woman on the stage… throw this affliction-without-remedy, enemy-of-morality-civility-and-faith woman immediately out of this Company (Al-Punch, 1891, 7/15).

In a long poem, on the decline of Dam_rī Theatre after its star actress Jawāhar eloped with Bādshāh Nawāb, the bodily beauty of the actress and sorrow of the spectators are expressed, significantly, with a blend of ‘morality’ and lascivious desire:

If old men get to see such a complete body, their old age will be taken care of,

And the condition of young men is worse than that of old men, Ah Theatre! When you could not satisfy your innate desire, you got the idea

And you subdued schoolboys, Ah Theatre!27

In yet another report, representing casteist segregation, it was lamented that no seating plans were made to segregate bāzārī women from the respectable members of the audience:

No separate seating plan was made for bāzārī women. Generally, they sat next to any person as per their desire (Al-Punch, 1899, 15/24).

The violence of representation of the subaltern women was brazening. And yet the disdainful lamentation that ‘they sat next to any person as per their desire’ signified self-respect that the ‘lowly’ women were gaining—even if it was at a nascent stage.

A report blamed ‘common people’ for the growing number of women performers in theatre, as they increasingly desired to see women nearby:

In the eyes of common people, women’s appearance on stage as actors is certainly considered praiseworthy, and for that very reason they rush in hordes. But the gentry consider it vulgar and do not look at such theatre with respect (Al-Punch, 1891, 7/15).

Participation in theatre was gradually transforming subaltern women into objects of marketized desire. Marketization generally denotes the privatization of public services within the welfare state (Kumlin: 2007). Marketization, however, herein denotes a capitalist marketization of social relations, which produces the petrification of true meanings of immanent human qualities. It commodifies, for example, women as objects of desire to be bought at a price affected by the market. Market manufactures commodified desire and presents it as innate to one’s being (for desire as an object, see Quaiser: 2018, 22-38).

Within the sphere of theatre, ashrāfiya casteist disdain and transformation of women into objects of desire to be consumed and owned go together. Thus, by the end of the nineteenth century, the expediently reluctant ashrāfiya were attracted to female theatre performers to seek lascivious pleasure from the object-desired-the easily accessible immoral women. A reporter L.H. Hamsar Bhāgalpuri wrote:

Why did you go to Calcutta? It is because the Harmistone Circus’ fearless, lustful…ladies’ riding intoxicated horses…. This generated lustful desire in spectators and clapping with great dejection. Pārsi Elphinstone Theatre’s taut-bodied girls’ and fairy-like boys’ dance with expressive action and gesture on stage, and on every step trampling upon the hearts of out-of-control spectators under the feet of coquetry. Such alluring and confounding plays were in Calcutta that you would forego thousands of conferences for each expression of those women....28

The power of masculine ashrāfiya social location to acquire the object desired was displayed quite brazenly in a letter to the editor, indicating a greater possibility of gaining easy access to and even ‘running away’ with the ‘women of lax morals’. It was lamentingly asserted:

Alas, I was not there, otherwise, right from the stage, clutching in my lap, I would have run away with at least one (of the actresses)29

Marketization with the underlying logic of the ownership of the desired object led to competitiveness among ashrāfiya. Jawāhar of Dam_rī Mukhtār’s Theatre was very beautiful, and many big wigs competed to possess her, but ultimately Bādshāh Nawāb was successful. In a poem, this event was commented upon, lamentingly and longingly for the body of the object desired:

I am faint-hearted; with grief, I am dispirited—Ah! Jawāhar With you went away the splendour of stage—Ah! Jawāhar What to say, what was that swelled-up breasts—that was stairway of beauty It was here that the travellers of intimacy boarded the train—Ah! Jawāhar Movement of lips was stimulant for eagerness—speech was magic In your sight was hidden Africa’s magician—Ah! Jawāhar Tell me, who sold you at Guzri30—O golden bird 31

With the progress of time, almost all theatre companies preferred to have women actors. For a fruitful survival of theatre, it must be economically viable, and for that to happen, female actors were much needed.

As is evident, a new subaltern subjectivity was in the making through the very act of subalterns’ participation in theatre as spectators and performers that constituted an act in defiance of colonizing the mind project through epistemic ashrāfiya-morality. The act of viewing32 assumed critical importance, as knowledge in print was the preserve of ashrāfiya and other literate castes. Subalterns did not have a neatly worked out schema for class struggle when they actively participated in theatre; instead, it was an expression of an impulsive, dormant, undeclared desire to say no to the undesirable state of existence marked by apparent silence, quiescence, servitude, meekness, passivity, submission to the ashrāfiya-morality as preordained. The desire to say no finds expression in many undeclared transferences (Quaiser: 2019a, 98-9). In the process, they learned mechanisms to act outside the given boundaries of epistemic ashrāfiya-morality. ‘Lowly bāzārī’ women, shudra Muslims and other labouring poor were driven by their existence in everyday life and its counter-intuitive comprehension; they learned imaginative manoeuvrings convivially.

Subaltern participation in theatre, however, was contradiction-ridden as well; for if theatre facilitated subalterns’ social visibility with emancipatory promise, the logic of colonialism at the same time was to subjugate them, and in times to come they would oppose the colonial power.

Section IV: Conclusion: Urdu Theatre Public Sphere, the Historicity of the Epistemic Ashrāfiya-Morality, Umma and Colonizing the Mind Internally

Urdu theatre in Bihar in the period of our study created an Urdu theatre public sphere. It became a critical source for comprehending not only the changing ashrāfiya moral, cultural and social landscapes but also of the making of a cultural history of subalterns. Thus, new discourses on gender, sexuality and ashrāfiya-morality; ashrāfiya perception of ‘corrupting influences’ of theatre; theatre enabling shudra Muslims and ‘lowly women’ to contest epistemic ashrāfiya-morality amounting to decolonize internally through their participation in theatre; a challenge to the ‘Muslim’/ashrāfiya/ ‘Islamic’ cultural identity and concerns to reform and preserve it; ashrāfiya collaboration with the colonial rule; colonial authority, English education, modernity, western moral values; and ashrāfiya and lowly castes’ responses to these issues constituted an Urdu theatre public sphere in Bihar. Within this sphere, unfamiliar issues, ideas, institutions, and a new language affected a new outlook, and the tensions that these produced engendered a sense of amazement, despair, lamentation, and attraction. Familiarity with the unfamiliar produced different routes for the ashrāfiya and subalterns. The ashrāfiya took the route of recognition of and negotiation with the colonial rule and continued with their epistemic morality. For subalterns, their convivial participation in theatre, questioned the ashrāfiya moral order, amounting to decolonize the mind internally.

The processes of colonizing the mind through epistemic ashrāfiya-morality that began with newer dimensions in the second half of the eighteenth century assumes critical significance. Assertion, contestation, recognition, negotiation, placation, and acceptance were the key ashrāfiya responses at different stages. The defining event of 1857 radically altered the social life of all segments of ashrāfiya, who portrayed the event as a big blow to mashriqyat33 and further ascendancy of maghribyat, causing attrition of distinct ‘Muslim’ identity.

However, mashriqyat has been a euphemism for ashrāfiya-morality and political power. Compelled against this turn of history, ashrāfiya began the construction of a subcontinental Muslim umma. Umma ideally denotes a united community of Muslims bound to Islam, independent of national boundaries. However, territorial conditions, local ashrāfiya’s interests, and ‘restorational politics’ (Quaiser: 2011, 49-68) ultimately shaped the conception of an umma. It meant, how to ultimately restore the lost ‘Muslim’/ Islamic (read ashrāfiya) political power, but since such a possibility did not even remotely exist, the only option left was to recover and sustain whatever could be recovered and sustained. This post-1857 concern and its postcolonial implications are best captured when much after 1947, Imārat-e-Shari‘a Bihar and Orissa, a prominent ashrāfiya institution established in 1921, introducing its raison d’être argued:

After the revolution of 1857 and the downfall of Mughal Empire in India, the ‘ulama of the day…were compelled to find out a suitable platform for the Muslims in India through which their social, cultural, religious lives and activities could be managed, controlled and guided in the light of Shari‘at laws…in non-Islamic countries. An organization based on Shari‘at laws under one Ameer (chief of the faithful) is essentially required to educate, inspire and guide the Muslim ummah to enable them to lead a collective life under Islamic order (Quaiser: 2019b, 173).

In Iāmrat’s conception of the umma, Islamic identity and the loss of Muslim political power assume critical significance. Certain other factors, such as the activities of Shuddhi Sangathan of Arya Samaj34 and the rise of Hindutva forces in the pre- and-post-colonial period also supplemented the umma-making efforts. Thus, the notion of umma became a powerful tool to colonize the shudra-dalit Muslim mind. In this conception of the umma, the ashrāfiya-perpetuated caste-based vertical division among the Muslims was strategically never even mentioned. The need to expediently construct a Muslim umma was/is for the preservation of ashrāfiya politico-religious oligarchic hegemony.

NOTES

1. Of ashrāf (of noble birth). Ashrāfiya herein denotes a hegemonic-highborn-casteist-racist-knowledge-oligarchy constituted by Muslim nobles of foreign origin and high caste middle-class Indian subcontinental Muslims. See the discussion in Section I.

2. Shudra is the lowest-ranked category in the Hindu caste system, under the subordination of Hindu upper castes. They are producer peasants, artisans and labourers, engaged in necessary material production and reproduction. Shudra castes constitute the majority of the Muslim population in the Indian subcontinent, retaining their ascriptive caste social status. Caste affiliations constitute their primary identity and are accordingly disdained by ashrāfiya.

3. Dalit means trampled upon, oppressed. The term Dalit was first used by Jyotirao Phule (1827-90) for the untouchable lowest castes in the Hindu caste system. Muslims too have their share of converted Dalits.

4. Urdu weekly Al-Punch was started in 1885 from Patna, the capital city of the north-eastern Indian province of Bihar. The weekly was read even outside Bihar. Al-Punch widely covered Urdu theatre activities in Bihar in the period of our study. Al-Punch covered national, provincial, local, suburban and international social, political, administrative, and cultural events and news. It supported the British Raj, as various post-1857 ashrāfiya-run Urdu newspapers did. Although, it was critical of the government’s various policies and practices with wit, satire, and humour but in a rather friendly manner. Al-Punch represented the post-1857 ashrāfiya intellectual ethos in Bihar through the emerging Urdu print culture. This essay is part of the author’s ongoing work on Al-Punch.

5. Maghribyat—Westernism: Western normative structure, moral values and philosophy of life and society, which in the given context included also the colonial state’s economic, political and cultural machinations.

6. Bāzārī (woman) herein means a woman portrayed as of lax moral, easily accessible for sexual gratification due to her low caste location.

7. Umma ideally denotes an integrated brotherhood of Muslims bound by tenets of Islam, devoid of caste-class-race hierarchies and independent of national boundaries. See Section IV for discussion (for a general concept of umma see: Shafi: 1997 and Esposito: 2004).

8. The term mazhab denotes a school of Islamic jurisprudence. The term maslak in the Indian subcontinent refers to multiple denominations within a particular mazhab, with conflicting interpretations of the Quran, hadīs, and Sunna. They are in antagonistic relations with each other as they also significantly represent non-faith caste-race-class interests.

9. Scholars studying ashrāf and their place in South Asian history (such as Margrit Pernau: 2013 & 2016) too have taken this ashrāf propelled representation as gospel. These categorizations are highly misleading, and they are only descriptive (which is also inadequate), and cannot be employed as an analytical category for comprehending ashrāf as a ‘caste’ social category. This is crucial, as this original theory has laid the ashrāfiya epistemic foundation on which subcontinental hegemonic casteist ashrāfiya subjectivity is constituted, which reproduces casteist hegemony to keep reproducing conforming non-ashrāf subjects. Most scholars studying ashrāf and their defining role in the ‘making of South Asian Muslim society and politics’ do not question the ashrāfiya epistemic foundations, and in doing so they endorse ashrāfiya hegemonic social locations. They can be called ‘docile’ authors as drawing on Foucault’s schematization of ‘the author’ Wael Hallaq has explained (Hallaq: 2018, 134-5).

10. Role of Islamic ‘canonical tensions and contradictions’ in expedient reinterpretations is a matter of another debate.

11. In Islam, akhlāq (morality/ethics) and ādāb (good manners) are traditionally rooted in Qur’an, sunnah, and hadīs. However, akhlāq has also been philosophically interpreted by Islamic scholars since the ninth century ad (See Fakhri: 1991; Hourani: 1985).

12. It has forcefully been claimed that the real author was Moulvi Hasan Ali (see Hasan: 1959, Eshara, 33-8; 31-6 and Hasan: 1962, 5-8).

13. Based on classical Urdu Masnavi (long, narrative, poem) Zahr-e-Ishq (1862) by Mirza Shauq Lakhnavi.

14. For males representing females on stage, see Hansen: 1998, 2291-300.

15. Bānkīpūr (or Bānkīpore or Bānkī Bazaar; also known as Bāqīpūr) is a neighbourhood residential area four kilometres west from the medieval Patna City or ‘Azīmābād, which came under the East India Company in 1764. Since the late nineteenth century, it signified a ‘modern’ locality.

16. Habermas identified a public sphere in eighteenth-century Europe where public issues were debated and the government’s activities were criticized by the ‘public’- the bourgeoisie (Habermas: 1989, 13 & 27). However, increasingly public sphere became status-quest to legitimise the capitalist state and society (Thompson and Held: 1982, 4-5; see also Calhoun: 1992). In the case of India, ‘as the historical context of public spheres in colonies was different from that of the western bourgeois society, the nature of the public sphere also differed. In India, public spheres existed much before the eighteenth century representing ideologically conflicting critical and conformist orientations outside the state. In India, it was concerned not only with the state and the political but also, with other indigenous structures of domination’, see Quaiser: 2012, 122. See also: Joshi, 2001, 23-58.

17. Gramsci employed the term subaltern for those who are excluded from political representation, thus hegemonically denied having their voice (Gramsci: 1971, 52-5). Moving away from the Subaltern Studies Group’s understanding (Ludden: 2003) or any mechanical class perspective, the subaltern is employed herein not strictly through and against the colonizer and colonized; instead to include also the non-colonial local caste-class forces of domination and forms of knowledge: the disenfranchized people of low castes; or at times even youth and student who felt suffocated under parental authority.

18. For subject formation and subjectivity, see Althusser: 1971, 123; Quaiser: 2019b, 180.

19. For popular, populism and authoritarian populism, see Hall: 1980, 157-85; Hall: 1981. For Frankfurt School’s views, see Jay: 1973.

20. Fazl-e Haq Āzād (1854-1942) was a landed ashrāfiya of Sayyed caste from the village Shāho Bigha in the Jahānābād district, Bihar, but later he settled in Bankipur in the 1880s.

21. Jān Sāheb (1817-96) is known for his Urdu poetry that detailed women’s sexual desires and activities.

22. These concerns were articulated more forcefully by various prominent ashrāfiya scholars.

23. Patna here refers to medieval Patna City.

24. Samik Bandyopadhyay has noted in a general sense that, ‘For the actresses, several of them single mothers or with dependents, the options were more constricted, and acting remained the only means of living’ (see Bandyopadhyay: 1994, 65-6).

25. Respectable educated men—plural of bābū.

26. For ashrāfiya lascivious description, see footnotes 28, 29, 30 & 32.

27. Al-Punch, 1892, 8/4: Passim.

28. Al-Punch, 1900, 16/24

29. Al-Punch, 1899, 15/18

30. Guzri—a residential and market locality in Patna City, where Badshah Nawab resided.

31. Al-Punch, 1892, 8/45.

32. Augusto Boal (2008) has underscored the possibility that the spectators could modify the representation according to their contextual experiences.

33. Mashriqyat: Easternism: Eastern normative structure and philosophy of life, which in the given context meant Islamic, ‘Muslim’/ashrāfiya-morality, Indo-Islamic, composite culture, indicating conflicting ideological predilections.

34. Arya Samāj was formed in 1875 for the revival of Vedic values and practices. It gained notoriety for its shuddhī activities for conversion to Hinduism creating communal tensions.

REFERENCES

‘Abdulwadūd, Q. (1952). ‘Urdu Indian Chronicle’, Mu‘asir: Part 3.

Ahmad, I. (ed.) (1973). Caste and Social Stratification among the Muslims. Delhi: Manohar Book Service.

Al-Attas, S.M.N. (1993). Islam and Secularism. Kuala Lumpur: International Institute of Islamic Thought and Civilization.

Alam, Muzaffar (2004). The Languages of Political Islam in India—1200-1800. Ranikhet: Permanent Black.

Althusser, L. (ed.) (1971). ‘Ideology and Ideological State Apparatuses’. In Lenin and Philosophy and Other Essays. New York: Monthly Review Press, p. 123.

Ansari, G. (1960). Muslim Caste in Uttar Pradesh: A Study in Culture Contact. Lucknow: Ethnographic and Folk Culture Society.

Anwar, A. (2005). Masāwāt Ki Jung. Delhi: Indian Social Institute.

Asad, T. (1993). Genealogies of Religion: Discipline and Reasons of Power in Christianity and Islam. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.

Bhatia, N. (ed.) (2008). Modern Indian Theatre: A Reader. New Delhi: Oxford University Press.

Bhattacharya, R. (1998). My Story and My Life as an Actress: Binodini Dasi. Delhi: Kali for Women.

Bandyopadhyay, S. (1994). ‘Theatrescapes’. Seagull Theatre Quarterly, 7, 65-6.

Boal, A. (2008). Theater of the Oppressed (tr. A. Charles, M.-Odilia L. McBride and E. Fryer). London: Pluto Press.

Calhoun, C. (ed.) (1992). Habermas and the Public Sphere. Cambridge: MIT Press.

Carson, T. (1984). The Status of Morality. Boston: D. Reidel Pub. Co.

Chandavarkar, R. (1997). ‘The Making of the Working Class: EP Thompson and Indian History’. History Workshop Journal, 43(1), 177-96.

——. (1998). Imperial Power and Popular Politics: Class, Resistance, and the State in India, c. 1850-1950. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Chatterjee, P. (1993). The Nation and Its Fragments: Colonial and Postcolonial Histories. Princeton: Princeton University Press.

Deshpande, S. (2008). Dalits in the Muslim and Christian Communities: A Status Report on Current Social Scientific Knowledge. Delhi: The National Commission for Minorities, Government of India.

Dumont, L. (1980). Homo Hierarchicus: The Caste System and its Implications. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press.

Esposito, J.L. (2004). ‘Ummah’. The Islamic World: Past and Present. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Fakhri, M. (1991). Ethical Theories in Islam. Leiden: E.J. Brill.

Fanon, F. (2001). The Wretched of the Earth (tr. C. Farrington). London: Penguin.

Gramsci, A. (1971). Selections from the Prison Notebooks (tr. Q. Hoare and G.N. Smith). London: Lawrence & Wishart.

Guru, G. ‘Janus-faced Colonialism in India’. The Times of India, 30 July 2005.

Habermas, J. (1989). The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere (tr. T. Burger). London: Polity Press.

Hall, S. (1980). ‘Popular Democratic vs. Authoritarian Populism: Two Ways of Taking Democracy Seriously’. In A. Hunt (ed.), Marxism and Democracy. London: Lawrence and Wishart, 157-85.

——. (1981). ‘Notes on Deconstructing the ‘Popular’. In R. Samuel (ed.), People’s History Socialist Theory. London: Routledge & Kegan Paul, 227-40.

Hallaq, W.B. (2018). Restating Orientalism: A Critique of Modern Knowledge. New York: Columbia University Press, 134-5.

Hansen, K. (1998). ‘Stri Bhumika: Female Impersonators and Actresses on the Parsi Stage’. Economic and Political Weekly, 33(35): 2291-300.

——. (1999). ‘Making Women Visible: Gender and Race Cross-Dressing in the Parsi Theatre’. Theatre Journal, 51(2): 127-47.

——. (2003). ‘Languages on Stage: Linguistic Pluralism and Community Formation in the Nineteenth-Century Parsi Theatre’. Modern Asian Studies, 37(2): 381-405.

——. (2016). ‘Mapping Melodrama: Global Theatrical Circuits, Parsi Theater, and the Rise of the Social’. BioScope, 7(1): 1-30.

Harmen, G. (1977). The Nature of Morality: An Introduction to Ethics. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Hasan, M. (2007). A Moral Reckoning: Muslim Intellectuals in Nineteenth-Century Delhi. Delhi: Oxford University Press.

Hasan, S. (1959). ‘Bihar kā Pehla Urdu Drama’. Eshara, 1(12): 33-8.

——. (1959). ‘Bihar kā Pehla Urdu Drama’. Eshara, 1(13), 31-6.

——. (1962). ‘Bihar kā Eik Gumnām Musannif—Muolvi Hasan ‘Ali’. Eshara, 4(7): 5-14.

——. (1959). ‘Bihar kā Urdu Stage’, Sanam, 2(8): 8-13.

——. (1959). ‘Bihar kā Urdu Stage’, Sanam, 2(9): 11-14.

Hourani, G.F. (1985). Reason and Tradition in Islamic Ethics. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Jay, M. (1973). The Dialectical Imagination: A History of the Frankfurt School and the Institute of Social Research, 1923-1950. Berkeley: University of California.

Joshi, S. (2001). Fractured Modernity: Making of a Middle Class in Colonial North India. Delhi: Oxford University Press.

Kumlin, S. (2007). ‘The Welfare State: Values, Policy Preferences, and Performance’. In Dalton, R.J. and Klingeman, H.D. (eds.), The Oxford Handbook of Political Behaviour. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1-23.

Lee, Joel. (2018). ‘Who is the True Halalkhor? Genealogy and Ethics in Dalit Muslim Oral Traditions’. Contribution to Indian Sociology, 52(1): 1-27.

Ludden, D. (ed.) (2003). Reading Subaltern Studies: Critical History, Contested Meaning and the Globalisation of South Asia. Ranikhet: Permanent Black.

Metcalf, B.D. (ed.) (1984). Moral Conduct and Authority: The Place of Adab in South Asian Islam. California: University of California Press.

Mignolo, W. D. and Walsh, C.E. (2018). On Decoloniality: Concepts, Analytics, Praxis. Durham: Duke University Press.

Momin, A.R. (1977). ‘The Indo-Islamic Tradition.’ Sociological Bulletin, 26(2): 242-58.

Mohammad, S.M.N. (1884). Jawan Bakht wa Shamsunnahār. Patna: Ahsan-ul Mat‘ab‘e.

Nāmi, A.A. (1962). Urdu Theatre (Vol. I). Karachi: Anjuman Tarraqi-e Urdu.

Pernau, M. (2013). Ashrāf into Middle Classes. New Delhi: Oxford University Press.

——. (2016). ‘From Morality to Psychology: Emotion Concepts in Urdu, 1870-1920’, Contributions to the History of Concepts, 11(1): 38-57.

——. (2017). ‘Love and Compassion for the Community: Emotions and Practices among North Indian Muslims, c. 1870-1930’. The Indian Economic and Social History Review, 54(1): 21-42.

P.S. Krishnan Report (2007). Identification of Socially and Educationally Backward Classes in the Muslim Community of Andhra Pradesh and Recommendations, by Government of Andhra Pradesh, Backward Classes Welfare Report.

Quaiser, N. (2011). ‘Locating the “Indian Muslim” Mind: An Incomplete Conversation.’ History and Sociology of South Asia, 5(1): 49-68.

——. (2012). ‘Unani Medical Culture: Memory, Representation, and the Literate Critical Anticolonial Public Sphere’. In P. Bala (ed.), Contesting Colonial Authority: Medicine and Indigenous Responses in 19th and 20th-century India. Lanham: Lexington Books, 115-35.

——. (2018). ‘Consuming Leisure not so Leisurely: Political Economy of Leisure and Desire.’ Explorations, 2(2): 22-38.

——. (2019a). ‘Parallel Praxis: History-domination-resistance-ideology-theory.’ In K.V. Cybil (ed.), Social Justice: Interdisciplinary Inquiries from India. London: Routledge, 73-110.

——. (2019b). ‘Shari‘a Politics, ‘ulamā and Laity Ijtihād: Fields of Normativity and Conviviality.’ South Asian History and Culture, 10(2): 173-80.

Rahmāni, I. (1987). Urdu Drama ka Irteqā. New Delhi: Educational Book House.

Rā‘īn, A. (2013). Bhaarat ke Dalit Musalman. Darbhanga: Heritage Publication.

Ranganath Misra Commission Report (2007). Report of the National Commission for Religious and Linguistic Minorities. Delhi: Ministry of Minority Affairs, Government of India.

Sachar Committee Report (2006). Social, Economic and Educational Status of the Muslim Community of India: A Report. Delhi: Cabinet Secretariat Government of India.

Sayyid, S. (2014). Recalling the Caliphate: Decolonization and World Order. Bloomsbury: C Hurst & Co Publishers Ltd.

Singh, L. (2010). Playhouse of Power: Theatre in Colonial India. New Delhi: Oxford University Press.

Shafi, M.M. (1997). Wahdat-e-Ummat. Lahore: Markazi Anjuman Khuddām-ul-Qur’an.

Thiong’o, Ngugı wa (1986). Decolonizing the Mind: The Politics of Language in African Literature, Nairobi: East African Educational Publishers.

Thompson, J.B. and David, H. (1982). ‘Editor’s Introduction’. In J.B. Thompson and Held, David (eds.), Habermas: Critical Debates. Cambridge: MIT Press, 4-5.

Trivedi, Prashant K., Srinivas Goli, Fahimuddin and Surinder Kumar. (2016). ‘Does Untouchability Exist among Muslims? Evidence from Uttar Pradesh.’ Economic and Political Weekly, 51(15): 32-6.

Vohra, R. (2001). Making of India: A Historical Survey. New York: M.E. Sharpe.

Wali Allah, S. (1995). The Conclusive Argument from God (Hujjat Allah Baligha) (tr. K. Marcia). Hermansen. Leiden: E.J. Brill.

*This chapter, with due thanks, is taken from: Explorations, ISS e-journal, 5 (2), October 2021. Earlier versions of this essay were presented at the conference on Colonial and Contemporary Bihar and Jharkhand, 8-9 October 2009, Delhi, in memory of historian Papiya Ghosh at CCMG, JMI, Delhi on 24 January 2014; and in the International Conference on Performative Communication: Culture and Politics in South Asia, 20-21 January 2015, Delhi. I thank Vibodh Parthasarathy and Arshad Amanullah for their comments on earlier drafts. Thanks to anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments, and to the staff of the Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library, Patna for their cooperation. All translations from Urdu are by the author. This essay is dedicated to my wife Raafia Raana Raheem.